Guide to the Tom Feelings Artwork
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tom Feelings artwork.
1958-2003
JWJ MSS 74
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.88
(31 boxes) + 77 framed items, 11 broadside folders
The collection consists of original artwork, dummies, prints and posters documenting Tom Feelings's work as an artist and book illustrator. The collection includes the original artwork for The Middle Passage: White Ships/Black Cargo, which consists of 51 drawings, currently housed in 47 frames, created in mixed-media tempera, pen and tissue, heightened with white and collage; the artwork is accompanied by 11 text panels that were part of a traveling exhibition. Other book illustration projects documented in the collection include Now Sheba Sings the Song by Maya Angelou, Soul Looks Back in Wonder, and I Saw Your Face by Kwame Senu Neville Dawes. Also found are numerous portraits of women and children, as well as drawings of a Civil War soldier, New York City, and street scenes that document Feelings's early career as an artist.
Feelings, Tom, 1933-2003
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company on various funds, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Tom Feelings (1933-2003)
Tom Feelings, artist and illustrator, was best known for his book The Middle Passage: White Ships/Black Cargo (1995) which depicts life on the ships that brought slaves from Africa to America. Feelings was born in 1933, grew up in Brooklyn, and studied at the Cartoonists and Illustrators School and later at the School of Visual Arts. In addition to The Middle Passage, Feelings illustrated numerous books, including Now Sheba Sings the Song (1987) and Soul Looks Back in Wonder (1993), which were collaborations with Maya Angelou, and I Saw Your Face (2005), a collaboration with Kwame Senu Neville Dawes, which was published posthumously. He was also a professor of art at the University of South Carolina from 1989 to 1996. Feelings passed away in 2003.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of original artwork, dummies, prints and posters documenting Tom Feelings's work as an artist and book illustrator. The collection includes the original artwork for The Middle Passage: White Ships/Black Cargo, which consists of 51 drawings, currently housed in 47 frames, created in mixed-media tempera, pen and tissue, heightened with white and collage; the artwork is accompanied by 11 text panels that were part of a traveling exhibition. Other book illustration projects documented in the collection include Now Sheba Sings the Song by Maya Angelou, Soul Looks Back in Wonder, and I Saw Your Face by Kwame Senu Neville Dawes. Also found are numerous portraits of women and children, as well as drawings of a Civil War soldier, New York City, and street scenes that document Feelings's early career as an artist.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Original Artwork, 1959-2003. II. Dummies, 1987-1995. III. Prints. IV. Posters.
Soul looks back in wonder; African American artists; African American illustrators; Art, American -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States; Illustration of books -- United States; Illustrators -- United States; Slavery in art; Drawings (visual works); Dummies (Printed matter); Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrators -- United States -- 20th Century; Angelou, Maya ( Now Sheba sings the song); Dawes, Kwame Senu Neville, 1962- ( I saw your face); Feelings, Tom, 1933-2003; Feelings, Tom ( Middle passage)
- Original Artwork, 1958-2003; Series I; 3.38; (24 boxes) + 77 framed items, 7 broadside folders
  - The Middle Passage: White Ships/Black Cargo (1995), 1993-1995
    Scope and Contents
    The entire suite of original mixed-media artwork, executed from 1993-1995 and published in 1995 book. Comprising 51 pieces in 47 frames, mixed-media tempera, pen and tissue, heightened with white and collage. Also included are 10 framed text panels and 1 unframed text panel that were part of the traveling exhibition.
    Individual artwork is untitled. The sequential numbers reflect the order in which the artwork appears in the published book.
    - The Middle Passage 1 [framed] (Box 1 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 2 [framed] (Box 2 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 3 [framed] (Box 3 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 4, 5 [framed] (Box 4 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 6 [framed] (Box 5 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 7 [framed] (Box 6 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 8 [framed] (Box 7 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 9 [framed] (Box 8 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 10 [framed] (Box 9 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 11, 12 [framed] (Box 10 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 13 [framed] (Box 11 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 14 [framed] (Box 12 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 15 [framed] (Box 13 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 16 [framed] (Box 14 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 17 [framed] (Box 15 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 18 [framed] (Box 16 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 19 [framed] (Box 17 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 20 [framed] (Box 18 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 21 [framed] (Box 19 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 22 [framed] (Box 20 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 23 [framed] (Box 21 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 24 [framed] (Box 22 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 25 [framed] (Box 23 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 26 [framed] (Box 24 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 27 [framed] (Box 25 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 28 [framed] (Box 26 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 29 [framed] (Box 27 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 30 [framed] (Box 28 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 31 [framed] (Box 29 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 32 [framed] (Box 30 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 33 [framed] (Box 31 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 34 [framed] (Box 32 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 35 [framed] (Box 33 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 36 [framed] (Box 34 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 37 [framed] (Box 35 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 38 [framed] (Box 36 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 39 [framed] (Box 37 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 40 [framed] (Box 38 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 41 [framed] (Box 39 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 42 [framed] (Box 40 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 43 [framed] (Box 41 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 44 [framed] (Box 42 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 45 [framed] (Box 43 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 46, 47, 48 [framed] (Box 44 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 49 [framed] (Box 45 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 50 [framed] (Box 46 Art Storage)
    - The Middle Passage 51 [framed] (Box 47 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 48 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 49 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 50 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 51 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 52 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 53 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 54 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 55 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 56 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text [framed] (Box 57 Art Storage)
    - Exhibition text (Box 118 Broadside)
  - Untitled alternative drawing for The Middle Passage [framed], circa 1995 (Box 58 Art Storage)
    Two ink, graphite, charcoal tissue, mixed media drawings. Depicts a sailing ship headed towards the continent of Africa. Featured in the touring exhibition of The Middle Passage.
  - Alternate drawings for The Middle Passage [framed], circa 1995 (Box 59 Art Storage)
    Pair of pen-and-ink, tempera and mixed-media drawings depicting enslaved Africans and sailors. Two drawings framed together. Drawings in the style of The Middle Passage.
  - Alternate drawings for The Middle Passage [framed], circa 1995 (Box 60 Art Storage)
    Three pen-and-ink, tempera and mixed-media drawings depicting enslaved Africans and sailors. Three drawings framed together. Drawings in the style of The Middle Passage.
  - Alternate drawings for The Middle Passage [framed] (Box 119 Art Storage)
    Captive Africans Being Rowed out to Slave Ship and Under the Ocean. Pen, ink, tempera, tissue, white and gray pencils. Two drawnings framed together. Both signed.
  - Proposed sequel to The Middle Passage [framed] (Box 61 Art Storage)
    One collage depicting a large central tree and figure, signed.
  - Proposed sequel to The Middle Passage (Box 62 Oversize)
    One pencil drawing depicting a large central tree and figure, matted.
  - I Saw Your Face (2005)
    A selection of drawings published in I Saw Your Face. Comprising: 27 original drawings, many worked into with color, some in brown-toned colored pencil. Includes the original illustration of a young woman used on the dust-jacket and cover, many portraits of young people, and some vignettes of buildings…All matted.
    - I Saw Your Face (Box 63 Oversize)
    - I Saw Your Face (Box 64 Oversize)
    - I Saw Your Face (Box 65 Oversize)
    - I Saw Your Face (Box 66 Oversize)
    - I Saw Your Face (Box 67 Oversize)
  - Soul Looks Back in Wonder (1993)
    The original artwork for the published book. Comprising: 15 mixed-media pieces consisting of original watercolor, charcoal, pen, ink and wash figural drawings over painted cut-paper collage…
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 68 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 69 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 70 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 71 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 72 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 73 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder [framed] (Box 74 Art Storage)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder, (6 drawings) (Box 75 Oversize)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder (Box 76 Broadside)
    - Soul Looks Back in Wonder (Box 77 Broadside)
  - Unpublished artwork from Soul Looks Back in Wonder (Box 78 Broadside)
    Mixed media collage depicting a young man holding a book flanked by two landscapes. Matted. Collage using motifs seen in Soul Looks Back in Wonder.
  - Other works
    - Civil War Soldier [framed], 1959 (Box 79 Art Storage)
      Original sepia toned drawing with wash depicting an African-American Civil War soldier. Signed "Tom Feelings 1959."
    - Campus Uproar (Civil Rights Struggle) [framed], circa 1960 (Box 80 Art Storage)
      Pen and ink, egg tempera.
    - Guyanese Girl [framed], undated (Box 81 Art Storage)
      Pencil, wash and mixed media on paper. Signed.
    - Untitled (Portrait of a Woman) [framed] (Box 82 Art Storage)
      Charcoal portrait of a woman in profile. Signed. Published in Now Sheba Sings the Song.
    - Untitled (Portrait) [framed] (Box 83 Art Storage)
      Signed pencil drawing. Published in Now Sheba Sings the Song.
    - Untitled (Portrait) [framed] (Box 84 Art Storage)
    - Untitled portrait [framed] (Box 85 Art Storage)
      Pen, ink, and sepia pencil portrait of woman. Signed. Published in Now Sheba Sings The Song.
    - Untitled (Portrait of a Woman) [framed] (Box 86 Art Storage)
      Colored pencils and paint depicting a woman in profile.
    - New York City drawings, circa 1958 (Box 87 Oversize)
      Group of eight drawings depicting New York City and New Yorkers, all drawn in the late 1950s. New York: 1958-1960. 8 ink, pencil, and whitewash drawings…All matted.
    - New York City drawings (continued) (Box 88 Oversize)
    - New York City drawings (continued) (Box 89 Oversize)
    - Early works, circa 1950 (Box 90 Oversize)
      Group of seven watercolors from early in Feelings's education as an artist. Watercolors on paper depicting street scenes with figures.
    - Drawings of women (Box 91 Oversize)
      Group of six original pencil, colored pencil, or charcoal drawings each in color or heightened with color, a few signed…Drawings are all portraits. All matted. One published in Now Sheba Sings the Song.
    - Portraits (Box 92 Oversize)
      Group of eleven large original pencil and brown colored pencil and charcoal drawings, a few signed…Drawings are all portraits. All matted.
    - Portraits (continued) (Box 93 Oversize)
    - Portraits of young children (Box 94 Oversize)
      Group of six large pencil portraits depicting young children. Some signed.
    - Portraits of young children (continued) (Box 95 Oversize)
    - Portraits of children (Box 96 Oversize)
      Group of five large drawings depicting children in pencil or charcoal, a few signed. Drawings are all portraits. All matted.
    - Portraits of children (continued) (Box 97 Broadside)
    - Portraits of young women (Box 98 Oversize)
      Group of four portraits in pencil depicting younger women…Some signed.
    - Portraits of women (Box 99 Oversize)
      Group of four portraits of adult women in pencil or charcoal, many signed…Drawings are all portraits. One slightly dampstained. All matted.
    - Portraits of women (Box 100 Oversize)
      A group of six drawings in colored pencils and pen depicting women, some signed, all matted.
    - Drawings of women (Box 101 Oversize)
      Four pencil drawings depicting seated women. Some signed.
    - Head studies (Box 102 Oversize)
      Group of six head studies in pen…Some signed.
    - Head studies of women (Box 103 Oversize)
      Group of five head studies in pencil. Some signed.
    - Head studies (Box 104 Oversize)
      Original pencil drawings, many signed. Drawings are all portraits. All matted.
    - Two Ghana Boys, 1965 (Box 105 Broadside)
      Oil on board. Signed and dated from Ghana, 1965. Matted.
    - Self-portrait, 1965 (Box 106 Broadside)
      Laminated large charcoal self-portrait executed in Ghana, West Africa, in 1965. Portions torn away. Signed.
- Dummies, circa 1987-1995; Series II; 0.5; (7 boxes)
  Includes three fully assembled sketch books with affixed printed images from The Middle Passage, and group of four maquettes, two with color covers.
  - The Middle Passage (Box 107)
  - The Middle Passage (Box 108)
  - The Middle Passage (Box 109)
  - Soul Looks Back in Wonder (Box 110)
  - Soul Looks Back in Wonder (Box 111)
  - [Now Sheba Sings the Song] (Box 112)
  - Press clippings, 1996-1999 (Box 113)
- Prints, Series III; (3 broadside folders)
  - Blood Knot (Box 114 Broadside)
    Hand-colored half-tone print. Signed and numbered 2/40.
  - Nude (Box 115 Broadside)
    Signed lithograph…Artist's proof.
  - Group of prints, including three artist's proofs (Box 116 Broadside)
    Group of seven printed including four labeled artist's proofs…Includes Blood Knot and Four Mothers. Some signed.
- Posters, Series IV; (1 broadside folder)
  - "... And Still We Survive," signed, 1997; (2 copies) (Box 117 Broadside)
  - "The Sapping of America's Strength," signed, 1987; (2 copies) (Box 117 Broadside)
    One copy is signed to Flo Kennedy.
  - " The Middle Passage: White Ships, Black Cargo," unsigned, 1995; (2 copies) (Box 117 Broadside)
  - Untitled poster from The Middle Passage, unsigned, undated; (2 copies) (Box 117 Broadside)